The French Revolution is the central political event in modern history.
You know, there are other things that compete.
The Russian Revolution, most obviously.
Or the American Revolution.
But I agree, neither of those really compare.
No.
To me, the French Revolution is the paradigmatic example
of people trying to reboot a society,
to make it again, to make something new.
So it's that on the one hand.
And then, of course, there are other dimensions to it.
It becomes the great crucible of conservatism.
It's in response to the French Revolution that Edmund Burke,
writes the most famous example of kind of literary conservatism in history.
It's reflections on the revolution in France.
It's the French Revolution that exports the idea of the nation
and of modern nationalism across Europe and arguably the world.
And its iconography, Tom, we're still so familiar with it.
I mean, obviously, it gave France its national anthem.
It gave it its flag, the tricolour flag.
But the idea of left and right comes from the French Revolution,
from where people sat.
In the National Assembly, right?
Yeah, exactly.
And when you think about all the great writing that's been done on it,
even just in English,
Dickens' A Tale of Two Cities,
one of the most influential books on our perception of history
that has ever been written.
You know, we mentioned Burke.
Dickens' influence by Carlyle and his great history of the revolution.
And of all the history books that have been written in our lifetimes,
one of the most influential on the way people write history,
I think, is Simon Sharma's book Citizens.
Some listeners may not agree with,
but Simon Sharma's take on the revolution,
his take is actually not dissimilar from Margaret Thatcher's
because he very much emphasises the violence and the costs of the revolution.
But the way he did it, the emphasis on narrative
and his ability to take unexpected aspects
and to take byroads and to make them so richly fascinating and colourful.
That's his great genius as a writer, isn't it?
Yeah, but that had an enormous impact on other historians.
I mean, it's a reflection of the inherent drama
and the scale and the sweep of the French Revolution
that it has inspired such great writers.
So there's Hilary Mantel as well.
You know, her first great historical novel
that's about the French Revolution.
Actually, it's for me, her best book.
Well, one of her, certainly her best historical book.
No, I think it's...
And what makes it so interesting is not just the high drama,
but obviously the questions.
Why did it all happen?
And even more than that, what does it mean?
Well, Dominic, we've answered that.
It's because...
Because of the diamond necklace scandal.
Right, so we can stop right now.
Yeah, we've solved it.
So to be very, very simplistic for a second,
if people are only going to listen to six minutes of this podcast
and they want to know why the French Revolution happened,
I think there are three ingredients.
One is there is a financial and a high political crisis.
Effectively, France is running out of money.
Number two, a social crisis.
So there's horrendous weather, freak weather.
There's...
There's famine.
There is kind of mass hunger in France.
So contingency then.
So contingency.
Playing a very important role.
And then the third thing, which is much more deterministic,
is a kind of cultural moment.
And I know you'll be talking about this in a subsequent episode.
An obsession with progress, with purity,
and above all, with virtue.
And an idea that you can turn the world off and back on again
and start again with a clean slate.
Forget about that.
Yeah, forget about the record of history.
And I think it is the combination...
The combination of those three things that makes it different
from the two obvious antecedents, which are...
Mrs. Thatcher mentioned the Glorious Revolution in Britain in 1688, 1689.
And then, of course, the revolution in the American colonies.
Although that is important, I think.
It is important, but this is qualitatively different.
Yes.
So the question is, why did those three things...
How and why did they come together?
And for many years, historians looked for big overarching ideological explanations.
But then,
really, especially from the 1980s onwards,
and thanks partly to people like Sharma or Robert Darnton,
another brilliant historian, American historian,
who has written about this period,
historians started to use the French Revolution
as the subject to reinvigorate the idea of narrative,
to say, actually, events really matter.
And the chronology, the series, the chain is enormously important.
But you ended last time,
you did that brilliant episode about the Diamond Necklace scandal.
And your point that all the discussion about Marie Antoinette
and her, the sort of the semi-pornographic,
well, I mean, very literally pornographic pamphlets and the abuse of her,
that reflected an idea that if, as it were, the body of the queen or the king were diseased,
that reflected a disease in the body politic.
And that's how we ended.
But we didn't say why the body politic was diseased.
So,
what is wrong with...
France?
I guess that is the question.
And to start with,
let's kick off with the man that you introduced us to, Louis XVI.
So you described him as, I think, very reasonably,
a kind of reasonably likeable,
but ultimately slightly inconsequential man,
mild, affable,
loves his locks, going hunting,
but not a man it is easy to hate.
So you look at Louis XVI and you don't see a man
who millions of people would want to see dragged...
He's not a monster.
No, he's not a monster at all.
He became king when he was 19 years old in 1774.
And actually, that's, you might say, a young man,
but actually, that's quite old for a French king.
Yeah, because usually they're toddlers, aren't they?
His grandfather, Louis XV, had been five.
His predecessor, Louis XIV, had been four when he became king.
So actually, Louis is not badly placed and he's been prepared for it.
His kingdom, as we discussed before, the biggest kingdom in continental Europe,
28 million people,
the world's second largest economic power, really, after Britain,
the only European country that has both the serious navy and a serious army.
Britain, for example, only really has a navy.
Paris, very different from today's Paris.
So it's the second biggest city in Europe after London,
but it's a city, it's not the kind of grand city of avenues and boulevards.
Yeah, because they will come in later than the 19th century.
It's a city of slums, but also, you know, it's typically the urban poor and prostitutes
and criminals, but also a city of coffeehouses and books and ideas
and newspapers and theatres and all these kinds of things.
And then beyond it, you have the other big cities of France also doing very well.
So France is unusual in having so many kind of provincial centres,
prosperous provincial centres, like Bordeaux and Lyon and stuff.
And then beyond that, eight out of ten French people work on the land.
In la France profonde, they are peasants, by and large.
So France is much, much more.
Agricultural than Britain is.
It is, and also much more kind of regionally distinct, really.
Yes.
Places like Brittany are very distinctive.
And you saw that when we were talking about the Cardinal de Rohan,
that he has a sense of his distinctiveness because he is Breton.
Yeah, absolutely.
So most, the funny thing about Louis XVI, Louis XVI would not have been able to understand
most of his subjects because they wouldn't have spoken what he would recognise as French.
They would have spoken dialects of French or they'd have spoken Flemish or Occitan or Breton.
Yeah.
Or German, all of these kinds of things.
So Louis has been brought up to be king.
And he, we think of him as an absolute monarch.
And he had copied out as a teenager a text to tell him that French kings had received from God himself
the greatest and most absolute power over other men that has ever been entrusted to one man.
But that absolute power is very tightly circumscribed.
So first of all, he relies on lots of other people.
He relies on judges and nobles and officials.
He's got his entendants, they're called, the royal officials that they send out to the kingdom.
If he loses their support, that's very bad for him.
He needs them.
Because he does have a famous exchange, doesn't he?
Is it 1787?
Where he basically, someone in the Parliament was saying this is illegal.
And Louis famously says it's legal because I say it is.
But that's a mark of weakness, isn't it?
Rather than strength that he has to say that.
Right.
Because France does have other institutions and constitutional conventions.
And they are so complicated that nobody really understands them.
So his grandfather, Louis XV, in the 1750s, had said, you know, France is such a kind of multi-layered, complicated machine.
I'd like to get all this written down on paper so I can make sense of it.
And he'd commissioned constitutional scholars to make a compilation of documents.
And they came back to him eventually and they just said, we're going to give up.
It's not possible.
It's much too complicated because it's a bit like Britain.
It is.
It is a massive patchwork of conventions and customs and laws.
But Dominic, you said you compared it to a machine.
And we talked about how Louis XVI is a great one for tinkering in a workshop.
Do you think that this is a frustration to him?
That he, as someone who obviously likes contraptions and working out how things function, that the state kind of defies his ability to do that?
I think absolutely.
Because I think Louis, like other people of his generation, is a product.
He's a product of the mid-18th century.
You know, he comes from a different world from Louis XIV.
He's an Enlightenment man to some degree.
And that doesn't mean he's sitting there reading Voltaire, but it means he's in that, you know, he's in that context.
Things can be solved.
Things can be sorted.
He's also been brought up, by the way, to respect what he sees as the rights of his citizens.
I know you're going to be talking a lot about rights in a subsequent episode.
And Louis had written down in his kind of exercise book as a boy that the rights of his citizens were light.
They were life, honour, liberty and property.
Not so dissimilar from the language of the American tax dodgers, Tom.
So his regime, the Ancien Régime, as people say, the old regime.
In your sort of Charles Dickens, Taylor Two Cities version of the French Revolution, it's corrupt and cruel, isn't it?
There's Marquesses kind of…
Running over paupers in their carriages.
Exactly. All of that stuff.
And very antiquated and reactionary.
In reality, that regime is very, very modern and is changing all the time.
Nobody says we are living in the Ancien Régime.
We're living in the old regime.
They think they are living in an age of enormous change and modernity.
And we mentioned already Simon Schama.
In his book Citizens, he's brilliant at bringing all this out.
And he says, you know, wherever you look as a historian, there are signs of great excitement and dynamism and energy.
So he mentions, you know.
French trade, French industry.
It's the home of chemistry, of maths.
Lavoisier, who will end up losing his head, won't he?
Both Schama and Robert Danton, in their books about this, emphasize hot air balloons.
Ballooning is a great spectacle and a great…
You know, French ballooning is the AI of the day.
It's something that people are talking about.
They don't know what world it will bring.
It's tremendously exciting.
The first flight was from the Bois de Boulogne.
In 1783.
And people would say, Robert Danton quotes some periodicals.
We live in the century of inventions.
We're surrounded by miracles.
Genius is everywhere, conquering nature and the elements.
And that's very Enlightenment, isn't it?
It's totally Enlightenment.
So Benjamin Franklin is a great hero in Paris.
And he's a great one for these kind of experiments.
Absolutely, yeah.
Because, of course, the whole American republic is an experiment, isn't it?
So America comes to be identified.
Both with nature and the kind of beauties and simplicity of nature,
but also with this idea of kind of progress, of modernity.
To what extent is the existence of the American republic
a kind of standing encouragement to people in France to think,
yeah, we could rebuild in that way?
It's a good question.
I think people are fascinated by the American experiment.
They're curious to see how it works out.
People like Benjamin Franklin are very popular in France.
But that said, if America didn't exist,
the French Revolution would still have happened.
Would still have happened, sure.
So I don't think it's a direct inspiration,
but I think some of the language definitely,
there's a commonality of language between the French and American revolution.
And just going on from that,
the crown support for the American revolution
obviously will play a key part in its ultimate bankruptcy.
But is there also a sense that the fact that a monarch
is going to the assistance of rebels against another monarch
an example of someone sitting on a tree, sitting on a branch
and sawing off the branch?
Yeah, I think it probably is.
I mean, there are people in the French regime
who are very nervous about the idea of doing this.
For that reason?
Well, they're more worried about the finances.
But I just wondered whether there was a kind of, you know,
an ideological anxiety about it as well.
Yeah.
Because Louis XVI seems not particularly to have been worried about that.
I don't think they're thinking about the American Republic
so closely as that, to be honest with you.
I think they're more interested in giving Britain a bloody nose.
Anyway, so all this excitement about change means you have two things.
You have people, we have a trend of sense of possibility on the one hand.
We can do anything.
We can conquer nature, so what can't we do?
And then the other hand, of course,
there are always people who lose out from change.
So in this, just to give you a small example,
if you're a weaver or an artisan or something,
there are new businesses, new industrialized businesses coming up
that may put you out of work.
And so you would like to blame somebody.
And we'll come to that later on.
As part of that modernity,
I think you also get a new political culture, especially in Paris.
This is not created by the French Revolution.
It creates the revolution.
Right.
Because we were talking about that in the context of the kind of
pornographic abuse of Marie Antoinette.
Yeah, the pamphlets.
Exactly.
Robert Danton's book, The Revolutionary Temper,
is absolutely wonderful on all this,
on the coffeehouses, on people swapping ideas.
People would read pamphlets out on street corners.
There's a new term, which we're very familiar with,
created in 1750 to describe this,
opinion publique, public opinion.
That phrase was not used before
because it didn't really exist in the same way.
So there's that.
But also I think there is also a really important thing,
which is a new language that people use to discuss politics.
So we were saying that Louis, you talked about him and the locks,
the idea of tinkering and the world being a machine and improving it.
And that's very much a product of the age of reason.
But actually, when he becomes king and he's 19 years old,
there is a generation emerging,
this kind of generation below him who are much more romantic.
They are the people who are loving Rousseau, Jean-Jacques Rousseau.
Well, but not entirely because Marie Antoinette,
who is his generation.
I mean, she's part of that.
I mean, she is the great embodiment of that in a way.
It's definitely younger people who embrace that.
But of course, it percolates out.
So Marie Antoinette is absolutely a classic example
of somebody who absorbs this cult of sensibility,
you know, nature, simplicity, all of these things,
intense feeling, tenderness, friendship, family.
And also the idea that if you obey the impulses of your emotions,
that will lead you to truth.
Yeah.
So it's kind of bizarre.
Isn't it?
That simultaneously, it's an age of reason,
but it's also an age of intense feeling.
And the assumption seems to be that the two,
well, there is a tension there,
but there seems to be an assumption that there isn't.
Well, I think there was a slight generational issue.
So I think if you were born in 1740,
let's say, you grow up in an age that is polite,
witty, ironic, sceptical.
Voltaire, you know, Voltaire is very sceptical.
They love poking fun.
There's always a kind of wry smile
at the corner of your mouth, that kind of attitude.
They're basically quite British.
And I think if you are a generation later,
let's say you're born in 1760,
then that scepticism and stuff,
you find that a bit desiccated maybe.
It leaves you cold.
What you're all about is your heart,
is living your truth, Tom.
Living your truth.
Yes, absolutely.
You know, tears, crying is really important to these people
and is important in the revolution.
Tears are seen as a sign of authenticity and honesty.
So people are always breaking down in tears
in the revolutionary story.
And the idea that underpins all of this
is the idea of virtue.
And I was thinking when I was writing the notes
how virtue in the French Revolution
is the diversity of its day.
In other words, it is an abstract noun
that if you have any decency as a person at all,
you're in favour of it.
And if you start to poke fun at it or to say,
well, I just think it's all overblown.
It's the emperor's new clothes.
I don't really agree with it.
People say, you're not just old, you're evil.
You say virtue.
I mean, you might more properly say virtus,
which is the Latin word from which the French word comes
and actually has the sense of manliness as well.
And I think one of the dimensions of the French Revolution,
which we will be exploring over the course of this series
and subsequent series on it,
is the way in which actually the kind of the egalite bros
are quite sexist.
Yeah, of course.
It is a very, very chauvinist movement,
I think, the French Revolution.
I think that's right.
So the man who embodies all this more than anybody else,
by the way, I think is Maximilien Robespierre,
and we'll come to him later on.
He absolutely drinks deeply of all this stuff.
So it's a very politicised world and very passionate,
but it is also, I think it's worth emphasising,
even before the Revolution, a violent world.
In Citizens, Simon Sharma famously wrote
that violence was not just a by-product of politics,
but violence was the Revolution itself.
And I think he's right,
but I think it's also worth emphasising
that France was already quite violent.
So any history of 18th century France
is punctuated by riots, lynchings, looting,
people being publicly beheaded,
prisoners being broken on the wheel,
troops firing into crowds.
So in other words, when the Revolution starts,
and it doesn't start with one thing,
it starts with a succession of things,
a lot of these things have already happened before.
They're not novelties.
The Revolution is not a storm breaking
from an otherwise placid, beautiful blue sky.
It's one storm cloud among many, Tom.
We talked about tax and finance.
So money is at the absolute centre of it,
and we should get into some of the money.
Follow the money.
Follow the money, exactly.
We should follow the money.
So all early modern monarchies
suffered massive money problems.
I mean, it's the story of the English Civil War.
It's the story of the American Revolution.
Monarchies trying to raise more funds.
And the reason they're doing that
is because they're living in a new age
with antiquated systems.
There's been a military revolution.
So they are funding bigger navies
and bigger armies than ever before.
But also they're doing it on a global scale,
which they weren't doing 200 years earlier.
You know, Britain, France,
they have to maintain fleets all over the planet.
And for France,
the fact that Britain has emerged
as a rival power
and a larger economy,
I mean, it's unsettling
because France has not had to face that before.
France has always been the largest power,
economically speaking.
And so that imposes massive strains, doesn't it?
When you're talking about the navy,
the Royal Navy is the key to British power.
And so the French have to have a navy.
But as you say, I mean, it's just unbelievable strain.
It is.
So France has been running up massive debts since the 1720s
and doesn't have a national bank.
Britain has a national bank,
but France, for various reasons, doesn't.
And France had had a kind of traumatic experience
with a slightly dodgy Scottish financier.
John Law.
It's a kind of tulip mania bust.
There'd been a massive stock market bust
and that basically turned them off finance.
So they distrust the idea of a national bank.
You know, that is when the word millionaire is coined.
Is that so?
Yeah.
Because so many people become so rich
and then they lose it all.
Tom, when Theo gives us an absolute roasting
for going over time,
it will definitely not be my fault.
Sorry.
So even before the American War,
France has already got very, very big debts.
It's got 2 billion livres in debt
and it's basically spending 60% of its budget
servicing that debt.
So on interest payments.
And this is growing all the time.
The interesting thing is that Britain's debt is much greater.
Britain's debt is three times greater.
But Britain can always raise new taxes
through the House of Commons.
The government needs no more money.
The House of Commons votes for it.
Bang, job done.
France can't do that.
Not only does it not have a national bank,
it doesn't have a regular elected assembly.
People do remember that there was once a thing
called the Estates General.
It was last met in 1614, 1615.
And nobody can really remember what it was,
how it was organized,
who voted for it or anything like that.
It's the existence of the British Parliament
that is able to raise money.
Is this something that in the build up
to the French Revolution,
people are looking at enviously and saying,
why don't we have a system like this?
Yes.
A lot of the revolutionaries at the beginning
basically want to turn France into Britain.
They want a more liberal economy
and they want a representative institution
or vote tax increases.
And they think, bang,
that'll magically fix all our problems.
So that's the Estates General.
That's the Estates General.
That's the only kind of precedent
in French history they have.
So France is raising tax
through a lot of very strange, antiquated things.
They've got a property tax
that a lot of towns don't pay.
They've got a very lucrative tax on salt.
But again, that just increases,
that means there's loads of smuggling.
And they have internal customs duties.
You are a miller in, you know,
Provence or something.
You want to sell your grain in Paris.
You have to pay multiple duties
to get your grain from A to B.
And that obviously is very bad
for the internal economy
if people are having to pay tax,
basically when they step outside their own town
to sell things.
And the kind of thing that a workman
in his workshop like Louis XVI
would want to fix.
Exactly.
So here's the thing.
Why don't they fix it?
Louis, when he comes in at the age of 19,
he's tempted by the idea of fixing it.
But the issue is that whenever he comes up
against opposition,
he almost always backs down.
So right at the beginning of his reign,
he had a bloke called Turgot
who was a liberal reformer.
He was basically slightly Liz Truss.
He wanted to go for growth,
deregulate the economy,
all of this kind of stuff.
He liberalized bread prices.
Of course, that meant the bread prices went up.
There was lots of looting.
And Louis eventually basically got rid of him,
said, you're pushing too far, too fast.
So Dominic, your case might be
that the problem with Louis isn't
that he is too despotic,
but that he's not despotic enough.
If he'd been a charismatic
and sufficiently adept statesman,
that he could take a bit of unpopularity
and he could persuade the people he needed
and he could show concrete results,
and he'd stuck to his guns,
he might have been a much,
much more effective King of France.
But as it is, what he will do is
he will always gesture in the direction
of change and then back down
when he gets into trouble.
So as Sharma says, and I quote,
he wanted to be loved.
And that is not an ideal thing for a King
in a time of tremendous change and challenge.
So in the next few years,
the problem actually gets a lot worse.
And it gets worse, as you said,
because they joined the American war.
So Turgot's eventual successor,
a guy called, a Swiss banker called Necker,
Jean-Jacques Necker.
Great name.
He says, you know, go for that American war.
Let's help the rebels in the American colonies.
And he organizes lots of more short-term loans
to pay for it.
Now, it's a naval war,
but as we know from the rest of his history,
nothing is more expensive
than an 18th century top-notch navy.
So they run up huge debts,
one and a half billion livres
on top of their existing debts,
90% of which comes from loans.
This will be a brilliant gamble,
by the way, if you get the Caribbean.
Because the Caribbean is so rich.
Yeah.
If you get that,
that's why they really have joined the war.
They want to get Jamaica, places like that.
But that requires them to inflict a defeat on Britain
more total than the ultimate defeat is.
So although the British lose those 13 North American colonies,
they keep lots of the rest of North America.
They don't lose any of the Caribbean,
which was their main priority.
And so actually,
the French have basically run up huge debts
and they've got nothing to show for it.
And Simon Sharma says,
without much exaggeration,
it can be said that it was the cost of the war
that brought on the terminal crisis of the French monarchy.
Should we get to the terminal crisis?
Yes.
So let's fast forward three years
to the year of the Diamond Necklace Trial.
So now we're in 1786.
The finance minister now
is a guy called Charles Alexandre de Calonne.
He's very rich.
He's very urbane.
He's very sort of witty.
He's a stock market player
and therefore everybody hates him.
You know,
for understandable reasons.
Bankers.
And in August 1786,
Calonne goes to see Louis XVI
and he says,
I've got a bit of a bombshell for you.
We are looking into the financial abyss.
He says,
our annual deficit every year is 80 million livres
and half of all our revenue
is now being spent on paying the interest
on our existing loans.
And he says,
what is worse,
NECA's short-term loans
that he took out to pay for the war in America
are about to fall due
and we don't have any money to pay them back.
And he says to Louis,
we have to totally reform the constitution.
We just have to sort out this problem
with the tax system once and for all
and get new taxes
because we can't rely on new loans
to pay the old loans.
So you may say,
well, what is this problem?
Why don't they just bring in new taxes?
And the reason is,
France is a society based on the idea
of hierarchy and privileges.
So if you are a nobleman or a clergyman,
you don't pay tax.
And people don't think of that
as a disgraceful exemption.
They think that's the essence of our liberties.
These are our God-given
and our ancestral rights as Frenchmen.
And it's a source of aspiration, isn't it,
for people?
Because it is possible to enter the clergy
or to gain patents of nobility.
So it's a kind of incentive
to stick with the system.
It is.
And also people don't like the idea
of a uniform system like a machine.
They say that is what will destroy liberty.
Liberty lies in difference and in quirks
and eccentricities and traditions.
And a government that tries to erase that
and just to put the stamp of royal authority
and say everybody must pay
is a despotic government.
And we don't want that.
We want people to stand up for our traditions.
And the people they want in particular
are these institutions called the parlement.
Now, confusingly, they're not parliaments.
Right.
So these are the ones that the parlement of Paris
that the Cardinal de Roma
opted to be tried by rather than the king.
They're courts.
They're high courts, basically.
And around them, so the parlement in Paris,
around them it employs hundreds of people,
clerks and stuff.
It's got its own kind of quarter of the city.
There's a whole kind of community of lawyers
and notaries around it.
And people invest it with tremendous,
you know, it's culturally very meaningful.
People invest it with a lot of significance.
The parliaments, these high courts,
when the king introduces an edict,
they have to register it.
And they have to say, yep, fine.
It doesn't contravene the rights of French people
that you as a king have sworn to uphold.
And what's happened, there's a pattern
that basically since the 1750s,
Louis XV and Louis XVI have asked the parlement
to approve to register new taxes
and the parlement has bitterly resisted.
And they have said increasingly,
the reason we're resisting the new taxes
is because we're defending liberty
against your despotism.
We're defending the nation
against your court in Versailles.
We're defending the ancient French constitution
against your suffocating, joyless absolutism.
And does the physical separation
of the king in Versailles
from the parlement, say, in Paris,
that presumably is enhancing that sense
of separation between the monarchy
and the sense the parlement have
that they are defending the people's rights?
I think so, Tom. I think absolutely.
I think it's a real problem actually
for Louis XVI. Geography.
The fact that Versailles is 12 miles from Paris.
He never leaves Versailles,
or barely ever leaves Versailles.
That 12 miles, most ordinary people can't afford
to take an expensive coach to Versailles.
So he's always slightly sealed off.
He's always in a bit of a bubble
and there's a real resentment of that bubble.
It creates the idea of a corrupt,
out of touch court.
And you get the sense that Paris
is this kind of place seething with political excitement
and theatre and new ideas and newspapers.
And Versailles is this sort of airless world
of snobbery and ritual.
And I think it's a really good point.
I agree with you.
I think it's a huge problem for Louis.
So anyway, Calonne says to Louis,
look, we've got this huge problem.
The parlement are never going to give us what we want.
We have to bypass the parlement.
We have to go over their heads.
I'm going to call an assembly
of the greatest men in the kingdom, the notables.
If they agree with this,
with the idea of the new taxes,
then maybe we can basically just ignore the parlement
and do what we like.
And this idea of an assembly of notables,
this is, again, something with the ancient precedent
that is being taken out of the lumber box
of antiquated traditions.
Exactly. Yeah, it is. Exactly.
And Louis says to Calonne,
I'm not sure about this.
I mean, this is a very big step
to try to bypass the institutions
to get this money.
And Calonne says, trust me,
if you do this, you will go down in history
as the man whose courage and foresight
solved the financial problems
of the French monarchy forever.
And the historian Jeremy Popkin
has a very strong line after this in his book.
He says, and so Louis XVI allowed Calonne
to set in motion the series of events
that would lead to the complete overthrow
of his monarchy.
This assembly of the notables
has gathered.
With what consequence?
So basically, Calonne has brought together
all the bigwigs in the kingdom,
princes, archbishops, judges, dukes,
all of these people.
And he says to them, OK, here's my plan.
We're going to abolish all these
mad tax privileges.
We're just going to have one tax
on landed property, and irrespective
of your social status, you'll have to pay.
So he is asking turkeys to vote for Christmas, basically.
He is, but he's saying, look,
this is in the interest of France.
Come on, we've got to do this.
We don't want to keep losing to the British.
Sure.
Number two, he says, we're going to lift
some of these mad, antiquated regulations.
Let's have the same, you pay the same duty
wherever you are in France.
Let's have freer markets so people
can sell across France.
Let's, you know, all of these vested interests,
we can relax some of these rules.
So we'll have more competition,
we'll have more growth.
And number three, he says, I know I'm asking you a lot,
so we're going to have elected local assemblies,
regular elected local assemblies,
and basically you, the landowners,
the bigwigs will dominate them.
So, you know, you'll get your way.
Your privileges will remain intact.
It's a very, very enlightened scheme.
It's a very mid-18th century scheme.
It's rational.
It's sensible.
It's kind of, let's have a bit of uniformity
and sort this thing out.
So it's not going to work, in other words.
Yeah.
And the notables just hate it.
They hate it because they don't like the,
obviously they're paying the land tax.
They don't like his plan for the assemblies
because they say, he says,
well, obviously you'd sit with the commons
in your province together in one assembly.
They don't like that at all.
They say the commons,
which they call the third estate,
they have to be separate.
We're not sitting with those.
Riff raff.
Great unwashed.
Yeah, riff raff.
And they say it's always the game
that these different institutions play.
To basically kick the tax increases down the road,
they say, you'd have to go through
and call the estates general.
I mean, no one really knows what that is,
but they sort of,
because they think it'll never happen,
I suspect.
They say, call the estates general
to approve the taxes.
It's like the Aztecs bringing out the owl.
Right.
It's the ultimate recourse.
You know, you need more representation.
Basically, we don't want to carry the can
for the tax increases.
You have to get a bigger body to do it.
Calon is really furious about this.
And now he does something
that is actually disastrous
from the perspective of the French monarchy.
He goes public.
He seeks to rouse the people.
He sends a pamphlet out to every priest
in the city in Paris.
And he says,
you have to read this to your congregation,
your Sunday sermons.
He has it reprinted in gazettes.
He has it read out on street corners
and read aloud to the crowds in Les Halles
in the big markets.
And this thing, he says,
he tells people,
France is at a crossroads.
You know, finances are in a total mess.
Either we have total change
or total collapse.
And in this pamphlet,
he uses a lot of the language
that anticipates the revolution.
So he's using terms like the national will,
patriotism.
He says,
the privileged will be sacrificed.
Yes, when justice requires it
and need demands it.
Would it be better to tax again
the unprivileged, the people?
And that kind of language,
people haven't heard that
from French royal finance ministers before.
He's anticipating a lot of the terms
that will be used in the revolution.
Now, when he comes out with all this,
the notables go absolutely ballistic.
You know, how dare you
rouse the people against us?
And so they complain to Louis about him.
So they complain to Louis.
And Louis, as is always the way,
Louis sacks him.
Sorry, mate, you've got to go.
People don't like,
the notables don't like it.
The notables don't like it.
As Sharma says in Citizens,
by taking his case to the public,
Calonne had made politics
a matter of national attention.
Once Pandora's box had been opened in this way,
it proved impossible to close the lid.
After Calonne, anything was possible.
We love a Pandora's box.
I like the fact that Sharma's gone for Pandora's box.
So the Pandora's box has been opened
and the storm clouds of revolution are gathering.
Definitely they are.
Now, the trouble is that,
so the debate has started,
a public debate.
People are talking about this in cafes,
on street corners and things.
And as amazing as it may sound to many listeners,
most people take the notable side,
the side of the very privileged people
who don't want to pay more taxes.
So Robert Darnton quotes journalists of the day.
Our notables,
which were thought to be puppets or courtiers,
are for the most part well-informed patriots
who know the true interests of the nation.
Because the one thing that people
are really worried about
is not the fact that nobles don't pay taxes.
It is they have a dread
of an overweening autocratic monarchy.
So the nobles are very good at posing
as the defenders of the French people's liberties.
And people believe it.
You know, people are roused by it.
But they're kind of riding a crocodile, right?
They are. Oh, totally. Yeah.
The notables are in for a shock.
Bit of a shock.
So now Louis has to find a new finance minister.
And he says, well, what I'll do is
I'll get one of the notables to do it.
I mean, that's quite a canny idea.
He gets a guy who's the Archbishop of Toulouse
who'd been a very outspoken notable
who's called Étienne-Charles de Lumigny de Brienne.
He's one of those kind of classic
late 18th century French bishops
who don't really believe in God or any of that nonsense.
There was talk of making him Archbishop of Paris.
Louis had apparently said,
surely as Archbishop,
he should believe in God, shouldn't he?
And Brienne also, entertainingly,
there's a lot of skin disease in this series.
There really is, isn't there?
So Brienne, I read, he suffered from a skin disease
that left his face, quote,
a mass of peeling scabs and tissue.
And yet he was thought of as a personable and congenial man.
So that says a lot for his personality.
It does.
Well, so we've had Louis XV
who died with his face covered in pustules.
And we're going to be meeting Marat, aren't we?
Yeah.
Mirabeau, the ugliest man in France.
Mirabeau, yes.
Yes, his face.
Well, yes.
So lots of big figures with unpleasant skin complaints.
Yeah.
So Brienne had been an opposition figure.
And he had said, like a lot of the notables,
I think Callon's stuff about the deficit is balderdash.
I don't think there really is a deficit, actually.
That's how I look in the books.
Oh, my God.
There'll be loads of money.
And he looks at the books.
He says, well, Callon, it's true.
Callon wasn't telling the truth about the deficit
because he wasn't.
It's not 80 million.
It's 140 million.
Oh, God.
So actually, Brienne then has to go back with his skin complaint
to his old chap chums in the notables.
And he says, actually, we do need new taxes.
And he wants a land tax and a stamp tax.
What could possibly go wrong with a stamp tax, Tom?
There's always very successful we's.
And the notables say, yet again, no.
No, we don't either.
So you will have to call the Estates General if you want new taxes.
Whatever it is, you have to call it.
So they scrapped the assembly of the notables.
So we're in 1787.
And Louis is very, very depressed by all this.
So there are accounts of him saying he's basically spent all his time
now going hunting and drinking and eating because he realizes.
I mean, it's amazing that he can go hunting because he's,
by this point, got incredibly obese.
So you pity the horse that has to carry him.
He's getting very fat.
He is very fat.
But it's a sad fat, Tom.
Not a jolly fat.
Oh, definitely.
He's not a jolly man.
No.
He's a sad fat man.
He's a sad fat man because I think he can see that this is going to be really difficult.
Well, because what options does he have?
Well, I mean, terrible.
Every option is bad.
So Brianne and Louis get together.
And what are we going to do?
They have two options.
One is they could just do what everyone says and call this Estates General.
But the issue with that is once you open that box, one of Simon Sharma's boxes,
where's it going to lead?
Like, will they have to have a constitution?
Will they demand more power?
Will you basically be reduced to being a British constitutional monarch?
And Louis doesn't really want that for obvious reasons.
I mean, why would you?
You'd want to keep as much power as possible.
The other thing they could do is they could go back to the old traditional thing of going through these courts,
these parliaments.
And somehow persuade or bully them into approving the new taxes.
And Brianne says, look, I'll do that.
So he goes to the Paris parlement, summer of 1787.
How about a stamp and tax?
How about a land tax, lads?
And the parlement of Paris say, no way.
And they reject them in very groundbreaking language.
They say, the days when kings just asked for taxes are gone.
Like, absolutism is over.
And the king must be governed by the law.
The nation must give its consent to new taxes with regular meetings of the estates general.
And for the first time, they use a word to describe their fellow Frenchmen that had not been used before by such institutions.
They don't call them subjects to the king.
They call them citoyens, citizens.
But the thing that's amazing about this is that it's in defense of nobles and clergy not paying tax.
Yeah, it is.
All this kind of language that will be used in the revolution.
The revolution that consumes both the church and the nobility is first being used to defend the privileges of the church and the nobility.
It is.
It's bonkers, isn't it?
And I think there's two things there.
One is that there's a degree of self-interest, obviously.
But the rules are also the idea that all the nobility are like this sort of Dickensian vicomtes who are like whipping their peasants and forcing themselves on sort of poor women and stuff.
A lot of these people are actually quite liberal.
Yeah.
They have absorbed the language of the Americans, of the American colonists.
And they genuinely believe in the Estates General and they actually do like the idea of a British constitutional monarchy.
And we talked about one of them in the previous episode, Philippe, the Duke of Orléans, whose Palais Real in the center of Paris is the great center of free speech of the pamphlets and will be the center for the Jacobins.
Yeah, exactly.
So there are people who genuinely, it's partly self-interest, but there are people, I mean, let's not pretend that there aren't people who genuinely believe this and really do think that this is a great way, that making a huge fuss about these taxes is a great way to get what they want in the long run, which is basically the British system, the system that had been advocated by the great Enlightenment writer, Montesquieu.
Let's have that in France, separation of powers, a proper legislature, all of that, prime ministers, all of that kind of stuff.
Anyway.
Brienne is outraged that the Parliament has rejected his plan.
And he now does something.
It does a couple of very, very drastic things.
First of all, the Parliament is exiled to Troyes in August, and literally it is sealed off by the Swiss Guard, by an elite unit of the French army.
And they're all basically kicked out.
And the reaction to that in Paris is total bedlam.
So if you had a time machine, you went to Paris in 1787.
You got out.
You would think that you're called.
Yeah, you got your wrong settings wrong.
You got the settings wrong because you'd think, well, this is the French Revolution because there is rioting by the clerks.
People who are giving out royal edicts are attacked by the crowd and two of them almost beaten to death.
A suspected police agent is beaten to death by the crowd.
And the government eventually has to send in infantry units to secure the streets of the capital.
And they end up shutting down.
Loads of clubs and societies.
They even shut down chess clubs because they don't want subversive ideas to spread.
And there's the real sense from 1787 from this point that the capital is, dare I say, a tinderbox, Tom?
I mean, is it more than a tinderbox?
Has it already slipped royal control?
I think to some degree it has slipped royal control, actually.
And I think from 1787 all the way through to 1789, it's a question of trying to regain royal control.
And there are troops on the streets, you know, pretty much all the time from this period.
Because there is the queen being forbidden by the king to go into Paris.
Right.
Exactly.
So that's against this backdrop, isn't it?
The hostility to Marie Antoinette.
Absolutely.
Yeah.
So the months pass very uneasily.
And then in April 1788, Brienne unveils a new plan to try and break the deadlock.
And it's quite clever in a way.
What he does is he will strip these courts, the parlement, of their ability to kind of police royal edicts.
He will beef up the powers of the courts below them, the lower courts.
They'll take over a lot of the parlement's power.
And there'll be a new court set up, a plenary court, which will approve royal taxes.
And obviously he will stuff that court with his people.
And the parlement will just be reduced to basically arbitrating disputes among the nobility, which is a pretty pitiful kind of thing for them to be doing.
And again, there are massive riots in Paris.
There's great outpouring of rage.
But the interesting thing here, right, so much of the French Revolution story is told about Paris.
And you just assume the rest of the country is being dragged along in Paris' wake.
But that's not the case because the worst riots about the Brienne's parlement plan are in places like Lyon and Aix and Dijon.
So provincial capitals.
Where having a high court was very important to them.
I mean, it's not surprising, is it?
Because we talked about how France is a much more geographically diffuse country than, say, Britain.
And well, actually, you know, I mean, it's a bit like Scotland defending its distinctiveness against London.
Exactly.
Yeah.
What makes you distinctive is incredibly important to you.
Yes.
Imagine the government trying to scrap the courts in Scotland and saying, let's have just one British court.
I mean, imagine that.
Or the controversial church or whatever, which was.
Yeah, exactly.
Now, this brings us to the city where the French Revolution begins.
And it's an unexpected place, isn't it?
It is.
So I don't think the French Revolution begins in 1789.
I think it begins in 1788.
And I think it begins in Grenoble.
Yeah.
So justify that, Dominic.
So Grenoble, a city in the foothills of the Alps, southeastern France.
It calls itself the cradle of the revolution.
That's how Grenoble brands itself to this day.
It's a very ordinary place, which you might think makes it a weird place for the revolution to have begun.
But no, the ordinariness is the point.
That is precisely why the revolution begins in Grenoble.
Grenoble is the capital of the province of Dauphine, a long way from Paris.
Its regional distinctiveness matters to it.
And there's a parliament in Dauphine.
And there are loads of people associated with it.
Lawyers, journalists, useless writers, all of this kind of thing.
The kind of people you get on Twitter.
Exactly that.
People who spend all day sitting behind their computers firing off angry messages.
They owe their livelihoods to that court.
If it is downgraded or removed, they will lose that.
Also, Grenoble is a glove-making center.
And they're very good at making gloves.
They export them all over the world to America, to Russia.
But the glove-making business is in real trouble because all of these woes have led to an economic downturn.
And lots of people have been put out of work.
So there's a lot of anger.
So on Saturday, the 7th of June, 1788, the day the French Revolution begins,
Brienne has his edict read out in the marketplace.
It's market day.
And he has troops go to it.
And he's trying to basically take the parliament leaders out of Grenoble,
which is what he's trying to do across the kingdom, to take them out of their centers.
And the law clerks come out and they start haranguing people and shouting at people in the marketplace.
This is what's happening.
Isn't this terrible?
And it basically escalates from a protest to a general strike and then a huge riot.
They close the city gates.
They lay siege to the governor's house.
The authorities send in soldiers, but not enough.
People go up to the roofs of their houses and they get these tiles and they start bombarding the soldiers with tiles.
So it goes down in history as the Day of the Tiles.
The soldiers, as is so predictable, they lose their cool.
They start shooting.
They kill a 12-year-old boy and they kill a hatter.
And then the crowd go ballistic.
They're parading the bloodied clothes of these people around.
They start ringing the bells to summon peasants in from the countryside because, of course,
because it's market day, a lot of people have come in from the countryside already.
So they're sailing to the peasants.
Your relatives are under attack from the soldiers.
Come and defend them quickly.
So people are pouring into the city.
Basically, the crowd seizes.
The mob seizes the city.
They sack the governor's house.
Tom, you'll be gutted about this.
They ransacked the governor's natural history cabinet.
I saw that.
Yes.
And they took a stuffed eagle.
Yeah, I suppose.
I mean, I suppose you can't make an omission.
You can't make an omelette without breaking eggs.
Well, of course, as famously as has been remarked on this podcast, they do not actually make
the omelette.
So basically, there is an intra-elite attempt to kind of grab the levers of power.
But essentially, that fight between the kind of rival sections of the elite has been overtaken
by a mass uprising.
Yeah, it has.
And actually, Simon Sharma is absolutely brilliant on this.
It's one of the many, many fantastic insights in his book.
And we shouldn't make this.
It's the Sharma fan cast.
But he points out the judges are carried aloft by the crowd, the parliament judges.
But he says it's not clear at this point.
You know, are they the leaders?
They're not the leaders of the riot.
They're more like it's kind of its trophies, a bit like the stuffed eagle.
But they're also kind of its prisoners.
Right.
And this is something that will happen again and again.
So, I mean, looking ahead, it's an experience that the royal family will soon be.
Exactly.
Yeah.
And some of the older judges are very anxious about this and end up actually leaving the city.
They don't want to be associated with this.
But there's a younger generation who are enthused and actually see in the disorder and the collapse
of royal authority a chance to lead, to profit.
And the classic example of this is a guy who I think is, you can argue, is the first true
French revolutionary leader.
So, he's a young judge from Grenoble and he's called Jean-Joseph Meunier.
And he is just such a perfect example of a French revolutionary leader.
He's the son of a cloth merchant.
He's upwardly mobile.
He's 29, so he's young, as so many of them were.
And he's a lawyer.
He's a lawyer.
Yeah.
They're all lawyers.
They're all lawyers, aren't they?
They're all young lawyers.
And he's really ambitious.
They're basically like Athelstan members, Tom.
They're young lawyers of the Restless History Club.
French revolutionaries in waiting.
So, he has bought the office of a royal judge and he has actually become a very, very,
he's on the lowest possible rank of the nobility.
And isn't that always the way, classically, in a revolution, that it's the people, it's
not the poor, it's always the upwardly mobile who haven't got quite upwardly mobile enough?
Exactly.
And he sees this as a chance to jump up the ladder and to turn the ladder into his ladder.
So, he convenes a huge meeting.
On the 21st of July, 1788, outside Grenoble, at the Chateau de Wiesel.
The Chateau de Wiesel, if you go there today, it is the world's only museum of the French
Revolution.
And there's a reason for that.
Because you can argue, again, this is one of the absolute places where the French Revolution
began.
Well, particularly if you are the Grenoble Tourist Board.
If you're the Grenoble Tourist Board, exactly.
And at this meeting, he says, listen, we want free elections.
We want the Estates-General of Dauphine, each province to have its own Estates-General.
And when that's going to meet, and when that meets, the third estate, the Commons, should
have the same numbers as the other two estates, the Lords and the clergy, put together.
And they should all sit in one chamber, not multiple chambers like they have in Britain,
Lords and Commons, or one chamber so that the Commons can dominate.
In other words, majority rule, the general will, will dominate over the privileged.
The villages of the old order.
And a lot of historians say that is so groundbreaking and seismic that that is the true kickoff
point for the Revolution, the chain of events that will lead to the Revolution.
There's two other things that I think are really revealing about that meeting at Wiesel.
First of all, is the language is so 1793.
It's all about patriotic fire, sacrifices.
The law.
It should be the expression of the general will.
But the other thing is there is a darker side to it.
So for the first time, these people say our opponents are, we are patriots, but our opponents
are traitors to the patrie and they should be treated accordingly.
Because there's a kind of incipiently totalitarian quality to saying that you are the embodiment
of the nation.
Definitely there is, Tom.
Because if you are the embodiment of the nation.
Your enemies, therefore, aren't.
And by definition, the traitors.
Yeah, I totally agree with you.
I totally agree.
Now, of course, you can say there's a great irony here that actually even Mounier and
his friends have not really understood what happened in Grenoble.
That right.
That riotous day.
They think because they've been chaired aloft by the crowd, they think they're going to
control it.
And they are, of course, dead wrong.
And some of these people are going to end up dead and literally dead.
But I think what you have, what makes it so revealing is that it is indicative of this
change in the language and the sentiment that is happening in 1788.
Previously, all that stuff was about the old liberties of the French, that the government,
a modernizing government, is trying to squash.
But in 1788, you can see that language changing and people are now saying, let's, you know,
actually do something new.
Who cares about the past?
We can use this opportunity to draw up a new constitution.
Sharma gives a brilliant example of a lawyer called Volney, who wrote a journal called
The Sentinel of the People.
What does it matter to us what our fathers have done or how and why they have done it?
The essential rights of man, his natural relations to his fellows in the state of society.
These are the basis of any form of government.
So in other words, that they're going to take that the idea of starting again.
And they take the passion, the idea of virtue, all of that.
And that gives them, you could argue, what Robert Darnton calls a radically simplified view of politics.
And also it, I mean, it's very contrary to the way that the Constitution has evolved in Britain,
where the whole point of the relationship of the monarchy to the House of Lords and the House of Commons
has evolved over time and is rooted in the deep past.
So therefore, you can already see that Britain is starting to fade as a model for the more radical proponents of a new constitution.
But also what is so interesting is it is also different from the American constitution makers.
Because they're, I mean, they're basically, the American constitution makers are slightly trapped within the British mindset.
So there, it's about the separation of powers.
They want to insure against a kind of mob democracy.
They want to insure against somebody having too much power.
It's kind of, their constitution is hedged about with kind of nuances and qualifications.
The French revolutionists have no time for that.
Sharma quotes a guy who was a friend of Rousseau's called the Comte d'Entregues, who said,
the people is the state itself.
By the immutable laws of nature, the people is everything.
Everything should be subordinated to the people.
That is not how British Whig politicians spoke.
It's not really how American politicians spoke.
Colonists spoke.
This sense of, it's very simple.
There's us, the side of virtue and patriotism and liberty.
And then there's them, despotism and depredations and corruption and all of that sort of stuff.
And traitors.
So right there, even before the fall of the Bastille, you've got the lines being drawn very starkly.
Now, meanwhile, Mr. Brienne with his pustules, the archbishop is sitting there in Versailles thinking,
what on earth am I going to do?
And he, and clearly everything is all kicked off.
His plan hasn't really worked.
And he says to Louis, listen, you have to call the, we do have to call the Estates General.
We're going to have to do this.
And Louis says to him, what archbishop?
You must think we are lost.
They might overturn the state and the monarchy.
And Brienne says, I'm afraid we have no choice at all.
So in the second week of August 1788, they go public and they say, we're going to call the Estates General.
We'll figure out how it will work in due course.
We don't really know what the rules will be, how it will be elected, but we will call it all the same.
What could possibly go wrong?
And then against this background, a massive development.
On the 16th of August, Brienne announces they have run out of money.
They have been surviving all this time on loans, but the royal treasury is virtually empty.
From now on, people will be paid in IOUs in paper money, which they don't really believe exists.
In other words, France is bankrupt.
Well, Dominic, what a cliffhanger.
So in the next episode, the Estates General will be meeting.
The revolution will be beginning, or you could, if you accept that it's already begun in Grenoble, it will be continuing.
And if you just can't wait to find out what happens, you can hear it right now by joining the Restless History Club at therestlesshistory.com.
Alternatively, the next episode will be coming very soon.
Either way, we'll see you then.
Bye bye.
Bye.